This drone is hovering over a compound
in Kaliscoco, Mexico. Suddenly, its
infrared camera captures a man. He hugs
two children and then a woman in what
looks like a long and intimate goodbye.
The man's name is Nessia Rubin Oera
Cantes, but he's better known by his
street name, El Meno. He may be the
world's most wanted drug lord. He's the
leader of the most violent and probably
the most powerful cartel in Mexico. It's
associated with 81% of all cartel
related homicides in the country. It's
essentially declared war on the Mexican
state and is flooding the world with
illicit drugs. For decades, Elmano has
always been one step ahead of the
authorities. Hardly anyone even knows
what he currently looks like. Usually,
he runs his criminal empire from a
secluded hideout, heavily protected by
landmines and over 60 gunmen. But today,
he's left his fortress. It's a rare
opportunity to finally capture him.
Since drug cartels operate in the
shadows, reliable information is often
hard to come by and few figures are more
elusive than Elmano. Using media
reports, official information, and this
book, we were able to retrace his steps
and piece together his story. Chapter 1,
Mitchan.
It's the early 2000s. Mexico is a key
player in the global drug trade, but not
a unified one. Four major cartels fight
for control. Each is a serious
contender. The Sinaloa cartel, the Gulf
Cartel, the Tijuana Cartel, and the
Huarees Cartel. Each control certain
areas of the country. In cartel slang,
these are known as plazas. They vary in
size, but usually include key
trafficking routes to strategic
locations like border crossings and
ports. Alongside with the four major
players, several smaller cartels are
also fighting for territory across the
country. One of them operates here in
Mituakan.
Rugged mountains and dense tropical
forests covered large sections of the
state's 60,000 km. For a long time,
certain areas could only be reached
through a complex network of unpaved
paths and trails. Here, the police and
the government have little to no
influence.
It's also the home turf of the powerful
Valencia family. Officially, the
Valencia have built their fortune on
vast avocado plantations. As the
Millennial Cartel, one of the smaller
organizations, they rely on entirely
different crops. The plaza is secluded.
Fertile mountains provide the ideal
conditions for growing marijuana and
opium puppies.
One of the most important ports for
cocaine shipments from Colombia is also
in the region. From here, several major
trafficking routes head straight for the
US border. Millennial has become a
reliable supplier to the Mexican super
cartels, especially Sinaloa.
On the fringes of the Valencia family,
oh man, it's a million degrees in this
booth and I've got the summer cold.
Sorry, I keep meaning to make a doctor's
appointment, but these voiceovers don't
record themselves. Find a doctor, work
out if they take your insurance, call
them, get put on hold, then find out
they have an appointment in November
next year. Who has the time? You're
right. I could just use Zdoc, today's
sponsor. It does let you search for
local in-et network doctors, including
dentists, psychiatrists, and
optometrists. You can see the
appointment openings and instantly book
one. It's all online and easy, so you
don't have to pick up the phone. And you
don't have to settle for Dr. Random
McFerson one I saw. You can check out
reviews and profiles to help you figure
out who you actually want to see. And
appointments happen fast, usually within
24 to 72 hours. Sometimes you can even
score same day appointments and it's
free. You know what? As soon as I get
out of this vocal booth, I'm going to
click the link in the description or
head over to zdoc.com/fern.
You should, too. After all, you have to
book an appointment sometime. Might as
well do it through the good people who
sponsor our reporting.
On the fringes of the Valencia family is
a quiet, inconspicuous figure in his
late30s.
One day the world will know him as
Elmano. He'll meticulously shield his
private life from the public eye. But he
hasn't always done so.
Cantas is born in 1966 in a small
municipality in Mituakan called Agalia.
He grows up poor in a family of avocado
farmers. In fifth grade, he drops out of
school and at some point he starts
guarding the Valencia family's marijuana
fields. As he approaches his 20s, he
moves to the US, illegally crossing the
border into California. There, he works
as a drug dealer and learns the ins and
outs of America's growing meth trade. In
the late 1980s, he's arrested twice. The
second time, he's deported back to
Mexico. In 1992, American police detain
him again. Undercover agents catch him
and his brother Abraham selling heroin.
This time, Cvantes spends 3 years in a
Texas prison. At the age of 30, Cvantes
is again deported to Mexico. Washed up
in the state of Halisco, he becomes a
state police officer. In 1996, Elmano
returns to Mituakan and marries the
niece of El Maradona, the head of the
Millennial Cartel. Soon, he starts
working for his father-in-law. El
Maradona has close ties to drug baron
Carlos Rosales Mendula. Mendula is close
friends with the head of the Gulf
Cartel, one of the four super cartels.
and the two cartel bosses strike a deal.
The Gulf cartel will help the Millennial
Cartel move their drugs to the US
border, but the alliance is short-lived.
El Maradona starts an affair with
Mendula's wife. Mendosa bows revenge and
turns to the Gulf Cartel for help. In
2002, the Gulf Cartel sends 300 killers
from its elite enforcement unit, Los
Zettas, to meet your Khan. A brutally
violent turf war follows. Eventually,
the Zetas prevail. Shortly after, El
Maradona is arrested and the Millennial
Cartel is reportedly driven out of its
home state. Elmeno and other former
Millennial members regroup in the
neighboring state of Kaliscoco, seeking
refuge with the Sinalora cartel. They
agree to work as a subdivision of the
operation. For Elmeno, this marks the
beginning of a new chapter. He now works
as a hitman for Inasio Nacho Coronel,
one of Sinaloa's most influential plaza
bosses. Coronel controls the drug trade
in the state capital of Guadalajara, the
most important city in western Mexico.
And just like that, Almano gets a front
row seat to Sinaloa, growing into the
country's most powerful cartel.
Chapter 2, Kaliscoco.
It's 2006. Filipe Calderon has just been
elected as Mexico's new president. One
of his first acts is to declare war on
the drug cartels. Over the next few
years, he deploys around 50,000 soldiers
to hotspots across the country. And a
bloody military conflict between the
state and organized crime begins.
Calderon pursues the so-called kingpin
strategy. Take down their bosses and the
cartels will fall apart. During his
term, about twothirds of Mexico's most
wanted drug lords are either captured or
killed. One of the first affected is the
Millennial Cartel, now operating under
the Sinalora Cartel. When its two heads
are arrested, the group suddenly finds
itself without centralized leadership.
This power vacuum benefits one man in
particular, Elmano. In the last few
years, he's risen through the cartel's
ranks to become a top lieutenant. But
inside the organization, the atmosphere
is thick with distrust. Many cartel
members have been detained by the
police, and some even think Elmeno may
have conspired with the authorities to
seize control of the cartel. According
to the Spanish newspaper, Al Pais,
intelligence reports also suggest he
betrayed his predecessors. The tensions
eventually erupt into a power struggle
between members loyal to Elmano and
those affiliated with his rival, El Moa.
Elmeno comes out on top.
and he's thirsty for more.
In September 2011, 35 corpses are dumped
on a main road in the city of
Veraracruz. The bodies were members of
the Los Zetas cartel. It isn't just a
massacre. It's an announcement. An
entirely new cartel has arrived.
At first, the group calls itself
Matasetas or Zeta Killers. It claims
it'll free the region and its people
from the Zeta's reign of terror. But
soon the cartel reveals its true
identity. Cartel de Kalisco Nova Ganasio
or the CJNG for short. Elmeno becomes
their leader, leaving the Millennial
Cartel behind. And he'll usher in an era
of unprecedented cartel violence.
In the years that follow, the CJNG
becomes one of the fastest rising
criminal organizations in Mexico. Its
expansion is breathtaking.
Several things explain this. Elmeno
seems to play by a completely different
set of rules than other cartel bosses.
Strategy one, franchising. Elmeno runs
the CJNG like a business. At the top is
the CEO, him. He calls all the strategic
shots like where to expand next. Every
time the cartel pushes into new
territory, it absorbs its local groups
often by force. These local cells
essentially become franchises while
still operating independently. They
adopt the CGNG brand and send a
percentage of their profits to the top.
This structure allows the cartel to
spread across Mexico quickly without
needing to control every area directly.
But Elmeno doesn't just grow his
operation. He also makes it more
profitable. Strategy two, focus on meth.
From the very beginning, one of CJNG's
most important products is
methampetamin. As the years go by, the
cartel starts pouring more and more of
its resources into meth production.
Elmanual knows the trade from his time
in California. There he saw the rise of
super labs, large-scale facilities
designed to manufacture meth on an
industrial level. He copies the idea and
brings it to Mexico. The result is
higher productivity, greater efficiency,
and enough high purity math to satisfy
growing demand in the US. The Halisco
cartel becomes one of the most dominant
players in the global meth trade. But
meth is only one part of the business.
The CJNG also traffics cocaine, heroin,
and eventually fentinyl. The drug trade
turns Almano into one of Mexico's
richest kingpins. But he knows how
quickly the drug business can change, so
he makes sure he has other sources of
income.
Strategy three, diversification.
Before long, the CJNG has its hands in
almost every profitable sector of
Mexico's shadow economy. Its members
steal fuel from pipelines, extort local
businesses, including avocado farmers,
and smuggle migrants across the US
Mexico border. They venture into
livestock breeding, illegal logging and
fishing, and time share rental scams.
This diversification strategy makes the
cartel more resilient. If one income
stream dries up, others can be tapped to
compensate. But Elmeno isn't just
thinking about Mexico anymore or the US
market. He's already dreaming of
dominating the global drug trade.
Strategy four, internationalization.
The cartel also sells its drugs to South
America and Asia. Meanwhile, Elmeno
builds a vast moneyaundering network.
Law enforcement claims the scheme is
largely run by Losinis, a partner
organization led by Elmeno's
brother-in-law. The operation stretches
across multiple countries. Some of the
cartel's profits are allegedly invested
and laundered abroad, for example,
through luxury properties in Uruguay.
Shell companies and frontmen apparently
moved the launder drug money back to
Mexico. The CJNG also cooperates with
Chinese crime syndicates called Triads.
It's also believed to have laundered its
cash flows through various
cryptocurrencies.
Unlike other drug lords, Elmano doesn't
flaunt his wealth. Instead, he stays in
the shadows and tries to win over the
Mexican people. Strategy five,
propaganda.
From the very beginning, the CJNG has
marketed itself as a benevolent patron,
especially in rural areas. On public
holidays, cartel members reportedly hand
out toys, food, and kitchen items. In
some places, the cartel allegedly even
controls parts of festivals and events,
and it provides financial support for
education and medical care. On social
media, it exploits people's resentment
of economic inequality to attract
underresourced youth. It approaches
young people via chats in popular online
video games like Fortnite or Call of
Duty. And it posts videos glorifying
narulture to lure teenagers with the
promise of a better future. But the
reality couldn't be more different. The
main reason for Almen's success is his
unprecedented brutality.
Strategy six, violence.
By the end of Calderon's tenure in 2012,
cartel violence in Mexico has claimed at
least 50,000 lives. Tens of thousands of
people have disappeared. Authorities
continue to unear gigantic mass graves.
Every day, the media reports new
atrocities.
Calderon's war on drugs has failed. The
same year, Enrique Panetto becomes
Mexico's next president. His government
continues to pursue the Kingpin
strategy, and it sets its sights on the
CJNG.
In January 2014, security forces arrest
Elmano's son. About a year later,
authorities capture his brother-in-law,
who reportedly handled the cartel's
finances.
If the idea is to scare Elmano, it
doesn't work. Instead of backing down,
the drug lord essentially goes to war
against a Mexican state. In March 2015,
cartel gunmen ambush police cars. Five
officers are killed in a hail of
bullets. A month later, they attack a
police convoy with guns and grenades. 15
officers die. In May 2015, the CJNG
shoots down a police helicopter with a
rocket launcher, killing nine.
Following these events, Kalisco state
officials declare Elmano public enemy
number one. But the state isn't his only
target. He also fights several rival
cartels as the CJNG keeps pushing into
new territory.
It's the most violent cartel the country
has ever seen. According to estimates,
as of 2024, the group has been
associated with 75,000 deaths. Research
suggests that between 2013 and 2022, the
CJNG was involved in more than 80% of
all cartel related homicides in Mexico.
The cartel has been building up its
military power for years, recruiting
former soldiers, and acquiring armored
vehicles, drones, and rocket launchers.
Most of these weapons have likely been
smuggled in from the US.
One Mexican security expert suggests the
CJNG might even be better equipped than
the Mexican military. On social media,
cartel members proudly display their
weapons. Some post shocking videos of
dead bodies. The CJNG has always used
violence as a means of strategic
intimidation. It publicly punishes
rivals and uses abuse to force potential
recruits to join its ranks.
It's even said to run its own training
camp. On an American Spanish language TV
channel, a former recruit talks about
his experiences. Apparently, one of his
fellow prospects was killed on the spot
for making a simple mistake. Cartel
commanders then forced other recruits to
cut off parts of his body and eat them.
Observers compared the CJNG's methods to
those of ISIS.
And for a long time, Elmano and his
cartel seem unstoppable.
Chapter 3. Sinaloa.
In 2018, Andres Manuel Lopez Urador wins
Mexico's presidential election by a
landslide. He promises to end the
country's rampant violence. During the
election campaign alone, more than 120
politicians have been murdered. Ordor
wants to deescalate tensions with a
policy called hugs, not bullets. Instead
of confronting the cartels heads on, he
wants to address the root causes of
violence through social programs across
the country. Expectations are high, but
things don't go as planned. 2019 goes
down as the most violent year in Mexican
history. In 2020, the DEA calls the CJNG
the greatest criminal drug threat to the
United States. By then, there are only
two major cartels left in Mexico. The
Sinaloa cartel and the CJNG.
The rest have been diminished by
internal power struggles or pressure
from their rivals. What's left is a
fragmented landscape of roughly 200
scattered smaller gangs. Each controls
its own patch of territory. Some join
forces, others turn on each other.
Alliances and rivalries constantly shift
and violent clashes are frequent.
In March 2020, the DEA presents the
results of Project Python, a
multilateral inter agency operation
targeting the CJNG.
On paper, it's a huge success. More than
600 people have been arrested, including
several of Elmen's closest relatives.
His son is extradited to the US, his
daughter taken into custody, and his
wife arrested. 350 indictments are
issued. The DEA sees his drugs and cash
worth roughly $20 million.
Aleno seems to respond, as he always
does, with violence.
The Mexican judge who handled his son's
case is killed. A mayor in CJNG
territory is murdered and Mexico City's
police chief narrowly survives an
assassination attempt. Authorities have
linked the letter to attacks to Almano
and his henchmen. The message seems
clear. Anyone who goes after the CJNG
will pay with his life.
In the end, Project Python changes very
little. The CJNG remains intact and
Almen's empire continues to grow. He
also benefits from the fact that his
main rival is bleeding itself dry.
In 2016, authorities detained a Sinaloa
cartel's leader, the infamous
>> Awakening Manuel El Chapo.
That leads to a power struggle between
two factions. One is led by Sinaloa
co-founder Elmo, the other by El Chapo's
sons, who are known as Chapitos. For
years, this tack of war creates its own
fragile equilibrium. But in 2024, one of
the trapitos turns himself into American
authorities and brings down Elmo with
him. The capture triggers a violent
conflict between the two Sinaloa
factions.
In December 2024, the Chapito's leader
sits down with Elmeno.
According to an exclusive report by the
Wall Street Journal, the meeting results
in a deal. Elmano supplies the Chapitos
with weapons, cash, and fighters. In
return, he gets access to key smuggling
routes into the US. According to the
journal, the two cartels also agreed to
divide up the international drug trade.
Sinaloa will focus on fentinel, while
the CJNG will take over meth and
cocaine.
By now, the CJNG has become Mexico's
most powerful criminal organization. It
operates in almost every part of the
country.
The same year, the US raises the reward
for information leading to the arrest of
Elmano to $15 million.
In early 2025, the DOS designates the
CJNG and seven other Latin American drug
cartels as foreign terrorist
organizations.
President Trump calls on Mexico's new
president, Claudia Shinbomb, to finally
bring the cartels under control. A few
months later, he goes even further. If
Mexico wants, the US is willing to
intervene directly.
But it'll never come to that.
Chapter 4. Tapulpa.
By now, authorities have been trying and
failing to catch Elmeno for over 10
years. His usual headquarters is hidden
deep in the mountains, reachable only by
a 6-hour drive. The roads leading there
are lined with landmines.
Elmano hardly ever leaves. At least 60
heavily armed gunmen guard him around
the clock. He doesn't have a cell phone
and he doesn't allow any network devices
near him. Every message is delivered to
him in person. But despite his
exceptional caution, Almano seems to
have a weakness. He's believed to be
having several extrammarital affairs.
One of his lovers is this woman. Mexican
intelligence officers have located her a
couple of days ago. Since then, they've
been tracking her every move with a
predator surveillance drone. Elmenure
wants to meet with her, so one of his
confidants picks her up. He drives her
to this compound on the edge of a
forest. It's located in Tapalpa in the
state of Kaliscoco. Later tonight,
there'll be a party. The next morning,
the woman leaves. The drone is still
hovering above her, watching. As she
leaves the house, the drone's infrared
camera captures her hugging someone. The
Mexican investigators watching are sure
only one person can get that close to a
Kingpin's lover, the Kingpin himself.
This has to be Elmano. He must have left
his mountain stronghold. Immediately,
the authorities start preparing a raid.
Early in the morning, six military
helicopters approached the compound.
On the ground, Mexican special forces
and army raid the property. When they
meet with resistance from heavily armed
bodyguards, a fierce firefight erupts.
But Elemential security team is
significantly smaller than usual.
They're no match for the army's air
assault. Elmeno and two of his gunmen
manage to slip out the back and escape
into the forest. They hide in thick
brush and fire at the advancing
soldiers.
One of the helicopters is hit and forced
into an emergency landing. At least two
Mexican soldiers are injured. Several
cartel members are killed. And Almano is
hit and severely wounded.
Special forces seize the opportunity and
capture him. Up close, the infamous drug
lord hardly looks almost 60 years old.
His teeth are kept with veneers and his
hair and mustache are recently dyed. A
military helicopter flies him to a
hospital, but he doesn't make it. He
dies during the flight.
In the US, some celebrate Elmeno's death
as a major victory over the cartels. But
the CJNG is far from done. Just hours
after Elmen's death, the cartel reminds
the public of just how much power it
still holds. Catel operatives rampage
across 20 Mexican states, setting fires
to cars and shops. They block roads and
gun down at least 25 Mexican soldiers.
In total, more than 70 people die in the
raid and its aftermath.
Things calm down over the next few days,
but the message is clear. The CJNG can
throw the country into chaos at any
time. Elmenro is buried in a golden
coffin. The cartel's drug business
appears uninterrupted with its roots and
structure intact.
Even before Elmen's death, it was
unclear how much control he still had
over the organization. For years,
reports suggested he was suffering from
a latestage kidney disease. It's
possible that others secretly ran the
cartel's day-to-day operations for a
while already. Now, the CJNG is at a
crossroads. So far, no official
successor has emerged. Then Elman's
right-hand man, Eluli, was also killed
in a military operation. In late April
2026, authorities arrested another
senior cartel leader. But reports
suggest that several of Elmen's
confidants are ready to fill his shoes.
It's believed the strongest contender
might be a man called El Pelon, also
known as Elzerot.
He's Almeno's stepson, and he's been
part of the cartel's inner circle for
years.
The next months will show whether
authorities have actually managed to
deal the drug cartels a devastating blow
or if it's simply the next chapter in a
violent war that refuses to end.